<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4234.xml">
<!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info"
	ipr="trust200902"
	docName="draft-hab-tcp-ao-applicability-00"
	submissionType="IETF">

<front>


<title abbrev='TCP-AO Applicability Statement'>TCP-AO Applicability</title>

        <author fullname="Melchior Aelmans" initials="M." surname="Aelmans">
                <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

                <address>
                        <postal>
                                <street>Boeing Avenue 240</street>
                                <code>1119 PZ</code>
                                <city>Schiphol-Rijk</city>
                                <country>The Netherlands</country>
                        </postal>

                        <email>maelmans@juniper.net</email>
                </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Greg Hankins" initials="G." surname="Hankins">
                <organization>Nokia</organization>

                <address>
                        <postal>
                                <street>777 E. Middlefield Road</street>
                                <code>94043</code>
                                <city>Mountain View, CA</city>
                                <country>USA</country>
                        </postal>

                        <email>greg.hankins@nokia.com</email>
                </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Ron Bonica" initials="R." surname="Bonica">
                <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

                <address>
                        <postal>
                                <street>2251 Corporate Park Drive</street>
                                <code>20171</code>
                                <city>Herndon, Virginia</city>
                                <country>USA</country>
                        </postal>

                        <email>rbonica@juniper.net</email>
                </address>
        </author>



<date/>

<area>Transport</area>
<workgroup>TCP Maintenance &amp; Minor Extensions (tcpm)</workgroup>
<keyword>TCP-AO</keyword>

<abstract>
        <t>
                This document discusses the properties, applicability and operational considerations
                of using TCP-AO in different network and security scenarios. It intends to provide a
                rough guide how TCP-AO can be deployed to secure TCP based protocols and applications.
        </t>
</abstract>

</front>

<!-- ***** MIDDLE MATTER ***** -->

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

	<t>
	This document intends to explain the properties and applicability of
	<xref target='RFC5925'>"The TCP Authentication Option"</xref> in different
	deployment scenarios and highlight the improved security the technology offers when compared
	to <xref target='RFC2385'>Protection of BGP Sessions via the TCP MD5 Signature Option"</xref>.
	It also documents recommendations for deployment.
	</t>

</section>

<section title="Problem Statement of using TCP MD5 Signature">

	<t>
	The TCP MD5 Signature (TCP MD5) is a TCP option that authenticates
	TCP segments, including the TCP IPv4 pseudoheader, TCP header, and
	TCP data.  It was developed to protect BGP sessions from spoofed TCP
	segments, which could affect BGP data or the robustness of the TCP
 	connection itself [RFC2385][RFC4953].

	There have been many recent concerns about TCP MD5.  Its use of a
	simple keyed hash for authentication is problematic because there
	have been escalating attacks on the algorithm itself [Wa05].  TCP MD5
	also lacks both key-management and algorithm agility.  This document
	adds the latter, and provides a simple key coordination mechanism
	giving the ability to move from one key to another within the same
	connection.  It does not however provide for complete cryptographic
	key management to be handled in band of TCP, because TCP SYN segments
	lack sufficient remaining space to handle such a negotiation (see
 	Section 7.6).  This document obsoletes the TCP MD5 option with a more
	general TCP Authentication Option (TCP-AO).  This new option supports
	the use of other, stronger hash functions, provides replay protection
	for long-lived connections and across repeated instances of a single
	connection, coordinates key changes between endpoints, and provides a
	more explicit recommendation for external key management.  The result
	is compatible with IPv6, and is fully compatible with proposed
	requirements for a replacement for TCP MD5 [Ed07].

	TCP-AO obsoletes TCP MD5, although a particular implementation may
	support both mechanisms for backward compatibility.  For a given
	connection, only one can be in use.  TCP MD5-protected connections
	cannot be migrated to TCP-AO because TCP MD5 does not support any
	changes to a connection's security algorithm once established.
	</t>

	<t>
	Today's current routing protocols were geared towards a network with an irregular
	topology and low degree of connectivity originally. When they are applied to Fat-Tree
	topologies:
	</t>

</section>

        <section title="Implementation status - RFC EDITOR: REMOVE BEFORE PUBLICATION">
            <t>
                This section records the status of known implementations of the
                protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of
                this Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in
                RFC7942. The description of implementations in this
                section is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in
                progressing drafts to RFCs.  Please note that the listing of any
                individual implementation here does not imply endorsement by the
                IETF. Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the
                information presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors.
                This is not intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog
                of available implementations or their features. Readers are advised
                to note that other implementations may exist.
            </t>
            <t>
                The table below provides an overview (as of the moment of writing) of which vendors have produced implementations of inbound or outbound maximum prefix limits.
                Each table cell shows the applicable configuration keywords if the vendor implemented the feature.
            </t>
            <texttable anchor="table_ex" title="Maximum prefix limits capabilities per implementation" style="all">
                <ttcol align="center" width="20%">Vendor</ttcol>
                <ttcol align="center">TCP-AO implemented</ttcol>
                <c>Nokia SR OS</c><c>yes</c>
                <c>Juniper Junos OS</c><c>yes *</c>
		<c>Cisco IOS XR</c><c>yes</c>
                <c>NIC.CZ BIRD</c><c>no</c>
                <c>OpenBSD OpenBGPD</c><c>no</c>
                <c>Arista EOS</c><c>no</c>
                <c>Huawei VRP</c><c>no</c>
            </texttable>
            <t>
                  *Not yet in main release
           </t>
        </section>

	
</middle>

<back>

	<references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5925"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2385"?>
	</references>

</back>

</rfc>
